# 白的红的黄的 加上打的杏仁浆
White, red and yellow. Together with the apricot milk
# 这种组合
This combination is
# 绝配
Fantastic
# (杏汁桃胶煮艿芋)
Taro and Peach Gum in Apricot Milk
# shift forward 00:00:09,020
# 二伯好
Hello, Er Bai
# 今天刚强来了 大爷好
- Gangqiang is visiting us today
- Hello, Da Ye
# 好久没见了
Long time no see
# 大爷好 想大爷想师父了
Hello, Da Ye. I miss my master Da Ye so much
# 年轻就是好 小脸红糊糊的
Here's our young man! Look at those rosy cheeks!
# 二伯今天做什么啊
What are you going to cook today, Er Bai?
# 大爷你看见没有
Da Ye, look!
# 你看见原料你能看出来吧
You can tell from the ingredients, can you?
# 又把这现代化的东西用上了
We can once again make use of this modern thing
# 它这个是芋艿头 这芋艿多好啊
These are Yunai taros. Pretty good Yunai taros
# 超市有现成的
Bought from the supermarket
# 如果说家里没有的话
If you don't have it at home
# 买那个大芋头小芋头都可以
You can buy either large or small taros. Both are fine
# 那种小芋头削了皮一蒸一样
After peeling and steaming, those small taros also work
# 但是那个没有这个好看
But the presence is not as good
# 那个里面有点小黑斑似的
They look like having black dots inside
# 这个还软活
These are also soft
# 你看小刚强修了点儿芒果
Look, Xiao Gangqiang just peeled a mango
# 夏季特别适合
Perfect for summer
# 冰糖
Rock sugar
# 红腰豆
Red kidney beans
# 这是杏仁
These are apricots
# 你看这一天吃的玩意 桃胶
- What a consumption we have
- Peach gum
# 我看这还弄两个杏仁露
We also have some apricot milk
# 又是甜品
Another dessert this time
# 二伯现在对甜品比较感兴趣
Er Bai is quite interested in desserts recently
# 这些日子高兴就做甜品
These days, whenever I feel happy, I make some dessert
# 等我心情差点的时候 我就做黑料
When I'm not happy, I'll make some "dark cuisine"
# 开始
Let's get started
# 咱们先磨杏仁是不是师父
We start with grinding the apricots, master?
# 先把杏仁弄了 干杏仁泡了
Apricots first. Soak the dried apricots
# 泡开了就行了
Soak them well
# 这已经有杏仁露了 放它(杏仁)干嘛
We already have apricot milk. Why do we still need it (aprocot)?
# 增加香味
For a better aroma
# 这是食材啊 货真价实这是
These are genuine ingredients, you know
# 放点干净水
Some clean water
# 这是我们跟师傅走宴会的甜品
Our master and us used to serve this dessert at banquets
# 也有十来年了
It's been over ten years
# 跟牛奶似的
It's like milk
# 在酒店咱讲究做细一点了
# 译注：不太确定这句话具体什么意思，是说这里要做得精细一点，还是因为不是在酒店所以不用太精细？
If we were cooking at a restaurant, it has to be finer
# 下一步咱先把这个煮了 小芋头
- Next, boil it
- Little taros
# 乒乓球似的
Like ping pong balls
# 煮一会儿
Boil for a bit
# 下一步咱们把芒果切了
Next, we slice the mango
# 切成了小方块就行了
Just cut into little cubes
# 看着这五颜六色心情更加愉悦
Look at these colors. How pleasant, aren't they?
# 夏天本身就燥
Summer is hot
# 热吃也可以 凉吃也可以
It can be served either warm or cold
# 最好是凉着吃
Cold is better
# 热着吃也非常甜
Warm is also pretty sweet
# 再洗就已经没味了
If you wash more, the flavors are gone
# 我就要这色
I just need the color
# 行了
Good
# 这个你必须得煮透了
This has to be boiled through
# 煮软和
Boiled to soft
# 盖上盖儿再煮它一会儿
Close the lid. Boil longer
# 糖要不要煮 要煮
- Do we boil the sugar?
- Yes
# 你可以放进去了
You can put it in now
# 冰糖
Rock sugar
# 这些菜品我看了 完成一半了
I've checked it. This dish is half complete
# 这小菜出的
What a production!
# 不着急
No rush
# 不着慌
No panic
# 大爷您说中餐和西餐
Da Ye, speaking of Chinese and Western cuisines...
# 那天我跟他们探讨去
Last time I had a discussion
# 什么区别
What's the difference?
# 西餐做菜 做工精细
Western Cuisine emphasizes on a refined cooking process
# 标准化做得好
Very well standardized
# 但是中餐也有中餐的特点
On the other side, Chinese cuisine has its own characteristics
# 其实我们前期的工业化生产
Actually, our inudustrialization
# 还没达到一定程度
is not as advanced
# 让我们中餐还保持着原来的一些原始生态
This keeps some primitive aspects in Chinese Cuisine
# 这就是中餐特点 品种繁多 做工复杂
These are the characteristics. Varieties and complex processes
# (一道菜)适合你但是它有时候不适合我
(A dish) might be good for you, but not for me sometimes
# 适合川菜又可能不适合粤菜
Might be good for Sichuan Cuisine, but not for Cantonese
# 中餐它是讲究五味调和
Chinese Cuisine emphasizes on the combination of the five tastes
# 利用调味料的变化
Using variations in seasoning
# 让多种调料 让它出不同的味道
Use multiple seasonings to present a variaty of flavors
# 有层次感是
A layering of flavors
# 还有通过不同的烹调方法
Also, via different cooking methods
# 产生出不同的味道
We can present different flavors
# 还有不同的刀功
Also different knife skills
# 产生不同的形式
To bring out different forms
# 今天又没白来 每次都跟上课一样
- This trip is so worthy!
- Every time it's like a lecture
# 不但你有收获我也有收获
Not only you learned something, I also learned soemthing
# 我要省事 我就买一个大芋头
If I want to save some effort, I'll just buy a large taro
# 我就切成菱形了 切的小一点
I'll cut it into diamonds. Little diamonds
# 把它一切二
Cut it into two
# 切的还挺好
Great cutting
# 然后大爷您看这就差不多了
And then, this is basically done, Da Ye
# 差不多了咱们煮这个 腰豆
Then we boil this one. Kidney beans
# 这腰豆是本身是熟的
The kidney beans are already cooked
# 这桃胶 昨天一泡就行
Peach gum. Just soak it overnight
# 这头晚上泡的 已经软和了
We soaked it last night. It's already soft
# 这是倒杏汁了
We are pouring in the apricot milk
# 杏仁浸 这是关键
Apricots must be soaked. That's the key
# 榨好的杏汁
Freshly milled apricot milk
# 放在一块煮 让它这个香味释放出来
Boil them together, so that the fragrance can be released
# 这渣滓不能浪费 这渣滓能做好多好吃的呢
Don't waste the residue. It can be made into something good
# 熬点儿杏仁粥 在家里边这点东西被糟蹋了
Make some apricot congee. It's home cooking, we shouldn't waste
# 放这个碗里头
Put it in the bowl
# 千万别倒了 待会儿我打包走
Don't throw it. I'll take it back
# 真香 舍不得我得拿走
Smells so good. I can't waste it
# LL这里边也含汁
The drink also contain apricot milk
# 养人
Very nourishing
# 爱搁奶的可以搁奶
You can also add some milk if you like
# 再熬一会儿就黏糊了
Boil a bit more, it will be sticky
# 行了 放桃胶了
- Alright!
- Peach gum in
# 这桃胶一下去 就得关火了
As soon as the peach gum is in, turn off the heat
# 把火关了
Turn off the heat
# 出锅了
It's done
# 这甜品好
That's a nice dessert
# 冷喝热喝都好喝
Cold or warm, both are good
# 适合冬天 夏天都可以
Good in both Winter and summer
# 好了
Good
# 芒果烫一下 让它们温度保持一致
Blanch the mango, so that their temperatures are the same
# 行了
Done
# 杏汁香芒浸艿芋
Taro and Mango in Apricot Milk
# 这名好听
Sounds good!
# 谢谢二伯
Thank you, Er Bai
# 先让大爷尝尝
Let Da Ye taste it first
# 最大那块桃胶给大爷 养颜了
Da Ye got the biggest piece of peach gum. So nourishing!
# 真有好吃
Tastes so good
# 确实好吃
It's good indeed
# 芋艿 就小芋头 软糯
The softness and mushiness of Yunai, I mean the small taros
# 杏仁的香甜
The sweetness and fragrance of apricot
# 加上我们水果的果香
Together with the fruitiness of the fruit
# 再加上桃胶的滑嫩
And the smoothness and tenderness of peach gum
# 是一道很养生的一道甜品
It's a really nourishing dessert
# 不管冬天喝夏天用
Winter or summer
# 是一个甜品的上品
It's among the best desserts
# 大爷有点儿过高评价啊
Da Ye is giving a pretty positive comment
# 这就是实事求是
That's seeking the truth from the facts
# 谢谢大爷
Thank you, Da Ye
# 我一般不会夸人
I don't often praise people
# 但是我真要夸了 我就往好了夸
But when I praise, I praise to the positive extreme
# 这人都爱听好话
People all love positive comments
# 我听完好话我也挺舒服 确实好
- I feel so positive hearing such positive comments
- That's so positive
# 白的 红的 黄的 你看各种颜色
White, red and yellow. So many colors
# 加上杏仁 打的杏仁浆 妙用
Together with fresh apricot milk. Fantastic
# 其实这是我们综合论 传统的说
Actually, comprehensively speaking, or traditionally speaking
# 它没离开根本
It's not away from its origin
# 杏仁茶是根本
Apricot Cream is the origin
# 他又加了点儿杏仁露
He also added some apricot drink
# 这是一种结合
That's a combination
# 芋头不管是咸吃甜吃烧肉 没问题
Taros can be either salty or sweet, or braised with meat. These are all good
# 但是我们把它做成甜的 蜜汁的
However, we can also make it sweet, or "Mizhi" (cooked with syrup)
# 做成拔丝的 也非常好
Or "Basi" (covered in half-melt syrup). Also good
# 你说腰豆
And speaking of kidney beans
# 一般我们在中餐里边用的不是很广泛
Generally, we don't use it very often in Chinese Cuisine
# 广东菜多
Except in Cantonese Cuisine
# 但是它搁这里边起到一种豆香
However, it has the bean fragrance in this dish
# 而且这腰豆还不是产自我国
Besides, kidney beans do not originate from China
# 是一个进口食品
They are imported
# 最关键这点 桃胶
And the most important part. Peach gum
# 既时尚 又有营养
Both fashionable, and nutritious
# 所以这种组合绝配
That's what makes a fantastic combination
# 谢谢大爷了
Thank you, Da Ye
# 我得谢谢师父 我今天又学一招
I need to thank my master. Today I learned something new again
# 最关键甜度适中
Most importantly, the sweetness is just right
# 太甜了就不好喝了
It won't taste good if it's too sweet
# 今天又学一招 谢谢师父
I learned a new technique again. Thank you, master
# 我亲爱的大爷
Even my dearest Da Ye
# 都没有这东西
Doesn't have this thing
# 是吧
Right?
# 看看（这是）七几年
Look at which year it was
# 1972年1月
Jan, 1972
# 多珍贵
How precious
# 你看
Look
# 这过去我们很简单
In this past, it was simple
# 这就是对我们人生的激励
This is what encouraged us in our life
# 这是我75年的笔记
These are the notes I took in 1975
# 上海绿杨邨饭店的菜谱
Menu of Luyangcun Restaruant in Shanghai
# 辣子鸡多少钱
How much was a Laziji ("chicken in chili")?
# 很便宜
Very cheap
# 你看家常豆腐
And also home-style Tofu
# 这都有
It's also there
# 这是我抄来的菜谱
This is the menu I copied
# 你看
Look
# 酱爆子鸡
Jiangbao Young Chicken
# 是吧
See?
# 才七块钱
Only 7 yuan
# 这都是我抄的
I copied everything
# 然后记的笔记  菜怎么做
And then notes. How to cook
# 每道菜怎么做
How to cook each dish
# 是吧
See?
# 芙蓉虾仁
Furong Shrimps
# 你现在菜谱都没这么标准
You probably can't see so standardized recipes now
# 你看鸡蓉蹄筋是吧
For example, this Jirong Tijin ("Chicken mince with beef tendon")
# 这都是您扎实的基础
Very solid in the fundamentals
# 对
Yeah
# 你看我那时候拼盘
You know, when I was going to make a platter
# 我自己画的小花篮
I drew this little flower basket
# 拼成这样
Like this
# 是吧
See?
# 这是什么
What is this?
# 这也是画的之后我要做的这种
I also drew this for something I was going to cook
# 底下垫什么东西
What should be put at the bottom
# 是吧
Yeah
# 你看金鱼冷拼
Look at this Gold Fish Cold Platter
# 是不是 都要垫着东西
There has to be something at the bottom, right?
# 就概念的意思
Just the concepts
# 怎么拼
How to plate everything
# 画了一个操作方法
I drew a method
# 真细
So careful
# 这些东西
These are...
# 就是我在上海绿杨邨实习的
When I was an intern at Luyangcun Restaurant, Shanghai
# 有这么一个小本本
I had this little notebook
# 小本本
A little notebook
# 唯一的 这是七五年
The only one. It was 1975
# 七五年
# 我十六岁到今年了
I was 16 then. I keeped it till now
# 是留到现在珍贵珍贵
Precious. Really precious
# 你看其实这个东西不值钱
You know, this actually isn't worth a lot of money
# 但是记录你的人生
But it has record your life
# 你看（这个）
Look at this one
# 这都对这本也是
This one was also like...
# 也是八几年
In 1980's
# 我在华都（饭店）
I was at Huadu Hotel
# 我学习书画的同源
I was learning "the same origin of calligraphy and painting"
# 你看学习绘画
Look, I was learning painting
# 这是我做的笔记
These are my notes
# 为什么要学画画
Why did you learn painting?
# 因为
Because
# 那时候也是为了加强艺术修养
It was to improve my artistic understanding
# 因为你做拼盘
Because when you make a platter...
# 这时候多大
How old were you?
# 那时候20多岁
At that time, in my twenties
# 20多岁
In the twenties
# 染花的步骤
# 译注：不知道什么叫“染花”
"Steps to paint a flower"
# 你看正面染
"From one side, ..."
# 你看 是吧
See, right?
# 这都是您好好学习的笔记
That's the notes when you were studying hard
# 对啊
Yeah
# 这都是人生的笔记
These are the notes of your life
# 这叫什么
How does the saying go?
# 没有人能随随便便成功
There's no casual success